Finding Aid for Museum of Anthropological Archaeology (University of Michigan) Records, 1894-2011
Bentley Historical Library
Museum of Anthropological Archaeology (University of Michigan) records
1894-2011
1925-2011
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropological Archaeology
0375 Bimu 2
7.5 linear feet
The University of Michigan Museum of Anthropological Archaeology was established in 1922 as the Museum of Anthropology. The Museum is one of the major research facilities in the United States for the collection and study of archaeological and ethnological materials. The record group includes budget information, executive committee meeting minutes, topical files, and curator files.
The record group (donor no. 9273 ) was transferred by the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in multiple accessions, beginning in 2002.
Further additions were made to the collection in 2006 and 2014.
The Museum of Anthropological Archaeology records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. The Museum of Anthropological Archaeology records include materials in the following restricted categories: Executive Officer Records -- Box 6.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
Although anthropological specimens had been part of the University Museums' collections since the mid-1800s, it was not until much later that a discipline-specific museum was created for their research and preservation. Prior to the Museum of Anthropology's establishment in 1922, the earliest archaeological acquisitions came to the University Museum from the Wilkes Expedition to the Pacific from 1838 to 1842. Other significant collections were acquired by Joseph Beal Steere during his many trips to the Amazon, the Andes, the south Pacific and Southeast Asia in the 1870s through the 1890s. His expeditions to the Philippines began a long and continuing tradition of research in that area. Steere was also in charge of the university's natural history collections from 1876 to 1894.
In 1922, Dean C. Worcester, one-time curator of the zoological museum at the university, returned to Ann Arbor from the Philippines to obtain support for an archaeological expedition to investigate Philippine cave sites with Chinese porcelains. Professors Francis Kelsey and Alexander G. Ruthven lent their support and requested that Carl Eugen Guthe lead the expedition with funds contributed anonymously by Horace H. Rackham. Guthe agreed to lead the party, but only if a separate Museum of Anthropology were established to house the material collected.
Guthe's request was granted; in 1922 the University Museums were reorganized and the Museum of Anthropology was formally recognized. Carl Guthe was made the Associate Director of Anthropology in the University Museum. The collection of porcelains Guthe obtained during the three years of the Philippines expedition became the museum's most valuable single collection. Wilbert Hinsdale, formerly dean of the School of Homeopathy, was made custodian in charge of the Collections in Michigan Archaeology. Guthe's collections were housed in the basement of Angell Hall from 1925 to 1927, while Hinsdale's were located in the Museum Building.
In 1928, the Museum of Anthropology moved into the fourth floor of the just completed University Museums Building. The museum consisted of five rooms for collections, seven rooms for offices, a library, and an office. In 1929, Guthe was promoted to director of the museum. One of Guthe's many acts as director was to offer a doctoral fellowship in Aboriginal North American Ceramics to James B. Griffin. Griffin began the fellowship in 1933, completed his degree in 1936, then joined the museum staff. In late 1943 Guthe resigned as director of the museum and recommended that Griffin be appointed as his successor. Administrative conflicts stalled the appointment for several years, but Griffin was finally approved by the Regents as the museum's director in 1946. He held this position until his retirement in 1975.
Upon its establishment, the museum had been arranged into five collection-oriented divisions (also referred to as ranges): the Division of the Great Lakes, the Division of the Orient, the Division of Archaeology, the Division of Ethnology, and the Division of Physical Anthropology. The Division of the Great Lakes dealt with the anthropological resources of the state of Michigan and the areas of other states and Canada that border on the Great Lakes. After Hinsdale died in 1944, Emerson F. Greenman took charge of the Great Lakes Division until 1966.
The Division of the Orient was devoted to collections from Asia and the Far East. Benjamin March was the division's first curator, followed by Kamer Aga-Oglu. The Division of Archaeology was established for the study of archaeological collections around the world, with particular focus on North America. The Ceramic Repository of the Eastern United States, a central sherd repository for prehistoric ceramic materials from the region east of the Rocky Mountains and north of the Gulf of Mexico, was founded within this division in 1927. James Griffin served as curator of the division until he became director, and was succeeded by Albert Spaulding.
The Division of Ethnology was established to house ethnological specimens from around the world, with particular focus on North America. Its first curator was Melvin Gilmore, followed by Volney Jones. The Ethnobotanical Laboratory, a center for the identification and interpretation of plant materials utilized by Native Americans, was established within this division in 1938. The Division of Physical Anthropology was originally not provided with a curator and was essentially inactive until 1966, when C. Loring Brace was appointed as curator. From that point on, the division focused primarily on prehistoric skeletal collections from North America.
The Museum of Anthropology achieved substantial growth during Griffin's long tenure as director. The staff grew from four professional curators to nine, along with additional research associates and assistants. The museum partnered with the Department of Physics in the administration of the Radiocarbon Laboratory from 1949 to 1970; the lab was the second of its kind in the United States. Field programs were greatly expanded, with significant work done in Michigan, the Mississippi Valley, the Southwest, Western and Eastern Europe, and Israel. The museum also took an active role in the university's Department of Anthropology; the museum served as a training ground for most graduate students in archaeology and all curators held academic year appointments in the department, teaching courses and advising numerous doctoral students. Griffin served as chair of the department from 1972 to 1975.
After Griffin's retirement, Richard I. Ford, Curator of Ethnology, was appointed as director, serving until 1981. From that period to the present, the museum's directorship has rotated among the curators of the museum, who generally serve three- or five-year terms.
In February 2014, the Museum was renamed the Museum of Anthropological Archaeology.
The geographic focus of the collections has expanded, with additional curatorial positions provided for materials from Europe, Africa and Mesopotamia. The current ranges include Great Lakes Archaeology, North American Archaeology, Asian Archaeology, Ethnology, Physical Anthropology, New World High Civilizations and Old World High Civilizations. The museum currently has twelve curators, in addition to other professional and support staff.
Today, the Museum of Anthropological Archaeology is one of the major research facilities in the United States for the collection and study of archaeological and ethnological materials.
(A published history of the museum may be found in The University of Michigan, An Encyclopedic Survey. In addition to the historical materials found in this record group, information on the history and activities of the Museum of Anthropological Archaeology may be found in other record groups held by the Bentley Historical Library, most notably the James B. Griffin Papers.)
Directors of the Museum of Anthropology and the Museum of Anthropological Archaeology
1929-1943 Carl E. Guthe
1944-1946 James B. Griffin (acting)
1946-1975 James B. Griffin
1975-1983 Richard I. Ford
1983-1986 Jeffrey R. Parsons
1986-1989 John D. Speth
1989-1992 Henry T. Wright
1992-1997 John M. O'Shea
1997-2002 Robert Whallon
2002-2005 Richard I. Ford
2005-2011 Carla M. Sinopli
2011-2016 Joyce Marcus
2016-2017 James E. Penner-Hahn (interim)
2017- Michael L. Galaty
The Museum of Anthropological Archaeology record group includes budget information, executive committee meeting minutes, topical files, and curator files. The records are organized in three series, Budget, Topical Files, and Curator Files.
Anthropology.; Archaeology.; Anthropological museums and collections.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropological Archaeology.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; Griffin, James B. (James Bennett), 1905-1997.; Guthe, Carl E. (Carl Eugen), 1893-1974.; Ford, Richard I.; Spaulding, Albert C. (Albert Clanton), 1914-1990.
- Budget, 1926-1980
  The Budget series, 1926-1980 (1 linear foot), is arranged chronologically and contains budget requests and supporting information for the museum. Generally, there is one folder per fiscal year, through some early years have been filed together. The files include some personnel information about staff salaries and activities.
  - 1926-1935 (Box 1)
  - Trust Funds, 1933-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1946 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Budget Projections, 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
- Topical Files, 1894-2011
  The Topical Files series, contains a broad range of information about the museum and is arranged into three subseries of materials gathered between 1894-1990, materials added in a 2006 Addition dated between 1925-1969 and a 2014 Accession with materials 1975-2011.
  Within the 1894-1990 subseries, of particular note are annual reports, program evaluations, museum histories and background research, and minutes of the executive committee. The series also includes information on field and research programs, staff directories, and registration procedures.
  The 2006 Addition contains further information on research programs, staff records, financial accounts and graduate programs between 1925-1969.
  The 2014 Accession contains Executive Committee minutes dated between 1975-2011.
  - 1894-1990
    - Alumni Relations, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports, 1924-1935 (Box 2)
    - Broadcasting, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Brown Bag Lectures and Lecture Fund, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - Building, 1952-1960 (Box 2)
    - Ceramic Repository for the Eastern United States, 1928-1933 (Box 2)
    - Christy Cogan Memorial Fund, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Coleman Report, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - College Resources Analysis System (CRAS) Tables, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Curator Title Problem, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Development, undated (Box 2)
    - Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA), 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Equipment and Facilities, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee, 1975-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Exhibits, undated (Box 2)
    - Expansion Plans, 1958-1963 (Box 2)
    - Field Methods, circa 1937-1960 (Box 2)
    - Field Personnel and Programs
      - General, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
      - Applications, 1960-1968 (Box 2)
    - Ford Foundation Trainees, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
    - History, 1944-1980 (Box 2)
    - History - Background Research, 1894-1972; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Library (University), 1937-1939 (Box 2)
    - Memos and Flyers, 1975-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Archaeological Society, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Archaeologist, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Museum of Zoology, 1966-1975 (Box 2)
    - Museums Library, 1956-1980; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Program Evaluation Report, 1956-1974 (Box 2)
    - Publications - Occasional Contributions, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Registration Procedures, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Research Applications, 1956-1962 (Box 2)
    - Research Grants
      - BNS 8105371 (National Science Foundation), 1980-1990 (Box 2)
      - BNS 8209649 (National Science Foundation), 1982-1990 (Box 2)
      - DEB 8208298 (National Science Foundation), 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Research Proposals, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Staff and Student Directories, 1956-1983 (Box 3)
    - Staff Meetings, 1946-1972 (Box 3)
    - State of the Museum, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - University Museums, 1955 (Box 3)
  - 2014 Accession, 1975-2011
    - Executive Committee Minutes, 1975-2011
      - 1975-1980 (Box 5)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - 1983-1986 (Box 5)
      - 1988-1994 (Box 5)
      - 1995-1997 (Box 5)
      - 1998-2002 (Box 5)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2024 ]
      - 2005-2007 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2027 ]
      - 2007-2008 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2028 ]
      - 2008-2009 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2029 ]
      - 2009-2010 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2030 ]
      - 2010-2011 (Box 6)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2031 ]
  - 2006 Addition, 1925-1969
    - Folder Samples, undated (Box 7)
    - Aboriginal North American Research, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Aboriginal N.A. Cer. Research Notes, 1941 (Box 7)
    - American Museum of Natural History, 1930-1932 (Box 7)
    - Am. School of Prehistoric Research, 1926-1936 (Box 7)
    - Business Office, 1926-1936 (Box 7)
    - Business Office, 1937-1941 (Box 7)
    - Business Office, 1940-1947 (Box 7)
    - M.G. Chancellor, 1928-1936 (Box 7)
    - Conference of SE Pottery Terminology, 1938 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence w/ Staff, 1934-1939 (Box 7)
    - Current Records Awaiting Examination, Vouchers, etc. to be transferred to specific binders after Certification of Correctness, 1939 (Box 7)
    - Department of Anthropology, 1936-1938 (Box 7)
    - Department of Anthropology, 1938-1940 (Box 7)
    - Department of Anthropology, 1941-1943 (Box 7)
    - Editorial Office, 1929-1934 (Box 7)
    - Editorial Office, 1938-1940 (Box 7)
    - Educational Investigations, 1941-1942 (Box 7)
    - Expense Accounts, E.F. Greenman, 1938-1939 (Box 7)
    - Expense Accounts, 1940-1943 (Box 7)
    - Extension, 1926-1936 (Box 7)
    - Extension Division, 1937-1938 (Box 7)
    - Faculty Research Fund-Grad School, 1932-1937 (Box 7)
    - Goodyear-Inactive, 1937 (Box 7)
    - Gourley-Black Corresp., 1937-1938 (Box 7)
    - Graduate School, 1925-1936 (Box 7)
    - Graduate School, 1937-1940 (Box 7)
    - Graduate School, 1940-1944 (Box 7)
    - Guthe, Carl Eugen, 1921-1953 (Box 7)
    - Library, 1925-1937 (Box 7)
    - Library, 1940-1945 (Box 7)
    - Literary College, 1926-1936 (Box 7)
    - Literary College, 1937-1940 (Box 7)
    - Literary College, 1940-1943 (Box 7)
    - Mallory, Dr. Herbert J., 1926 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Historical Collection, 1932-1934 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-1940 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1941-1946 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Trust Funds, 1941 (Box 7)
    - Museum of Anthropology, 1931-1941 (Box 7)
    - Museum, 1937-1940 (Box 7)
    - National Youth Administration, 1940-1943 (Box 7)
    - National Youth Administration, 1936-1940 (Box 7)
    - Museums, 1926-1930 (Box 7)
    - Occasional Contributions- Acknowledgements, 1941-1944 (Box 8)
    - Occasional Contributions- Receipts, 1937-1940 (Box 8)
    - Occasional Contributions, 1940-1942 (Box 8)
    - Occasional Contributions, 1938-1942 (Box 8)
    - Odegaard, Charles E., 1953-1954 (Box 8)
    - Old Time Sheets + Payroll Records of Current Act (Partial), 1931-1943 (Box 8)
    - Personnel Office, 1940-1944 (Box 8)
    - Physical Anthropology of the Eastern United States Indians, 1936-1939 (Box 8)
    - President + Regents, 1925-1937 (Box 8)
    - President + Regents, 1937-1940 (Box 8)
    - President's Office (Regents), 1940-1944 (Box 8)
    - R #10, 1936-1939 (Box 8)
    - R #32, 1941 (Box 8)
    - R # 57, 1938-1940 (Box 8)
    - Rackham Fund- Eastern Michigan Indian HIstory, 1935-1937 (Box 8)
    - Receipts- Miscellanous, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
    - Schedule, 1936-1940 (Box 8)
    - Staff, 1926-1936 (Box 8)
    - Staff, 1937-1940 (Box 8)
    - Student Recommendations, 1938-1939 (Box 8)
    - Student Recommendations, 1942 (Box 8)
    - Telephone and Telegraph Charges, 1940-1943 (Box 8)
    - Towle, Dr. Margaret, 1960 (Box 8)
    - University-Alumni Relations, 1933-1936 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Aboriginal North American Research, 1941-1943 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Current Account, 1940-1941 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Accounts, 194-1943 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Accounts, 1943-1944 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Accounts, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Accounts, 1945-1946 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Accounts, 1946-1947 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Fellowships and Scholarships, 1939 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances R #10, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
    - U of M Finances Shop Orders, 1936-1948 (Box 8)
    - U of M Institute of Archaeological Research, 1934-1936 (Box 8)
    - U of M Institute of Archaeological Research, 1938 (Box 8)
    - University Museums, 1940 (Box 8)
    - University Museums, 1941-1946 (Box 8)
    - University Press, 1942-1943 (Box 8)
- Curator Files, 1946-1987
  The Curator Files series, 1946-1987 (0.25 linear feet), contains correspondence of two of the museum's curators, Albert C. Spaulding, Curator of Archaeology from 1951 to 1961, and Richard I. Ford, Curator of Ethnology from 1968 to present (as well as director from 1975 to 1981 and 2002 to present). These files mainly concern museum business and the curators' research and professional activities.
  - Richard I. Ford
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Albert C. Spaulding
    - Correspondence, 1946-1958; 4 folders (Box 3)